Let's discuss about Android architecture.
The Android system architecture is divided into five layers, as you can see in this diagram, from
top to bottom.
First comes the application layer, which contains the system apps and the normal application, and
then comes the application framework layer or the Java API framework layer, which contains all these
managers, activity managers, location manager, package managers, etc. And then comes the system
runtime layer which contains a Native C, C++ libraries and the Android runtime.
And after that, the hardware abstraction layer or the HAL, which contains the necessary logics for
audio, bluetooth, camera sensor, etc. And at the bottom most we have the Linux kernel layer, but
we have the drivers for audio bind to display, iPad, Bluetooth, etc. and at the bottom we have the
power management.
So these are the five layers of Android architecture.
Let's dig deeper into each of these components.
In the application layer, both built in applications and not system level applications exists, but
they are basically responsible for more and better connection with the users and they are usually developed
in Java or Kotlin and these apps are mostly developed by the application developers.
And also there are the building stock apps which comes as part of a being to look at these system apps
or the stock apps in a later session.
The Application Framework layer provides developers with the APIs needed to develop applications.
This layer is written in Java and it can be also called Java framework.
But nowadays there are some frameworks written in Kotlin ask for them.
We usually develop the applications, I mean the Android applications that can call the APIs provided
by this particular layer.
Let's look at the main components provided by the application layer.
So first we have the activity manager.
So activity manager is mainly responsible for managing the lifecycle of each application.
So each application is built with different activities or fragments.
So it is the responsibility of the activity manager to manage the lifecycle of each application or each
activity within the application.
Next is the location manager.
The location manager provides the geographic location and positioning functions are resource.
For example, the maps will be using the location manager to get the current location of the device.
Package Manager.
Package Manager manages all applications installed into Android system.
It's basically responsible for installing and installing and giving permissions with the applications
installed in the Android system.
Notification Manager.
Notification Manager allows the application to display custom prompt information in the status bar.
So for example, when you get an email, for example, in the Gmail app, you get a message added at
the notification that you have an email that is done through the notification manager and then comes
the resource manager.
It provides various non code resources that application user such as the localized to strings, pictures,
layout files, color files, etc...
So if you are from an Android application development background, you definitely know localized strings,
pictures, loud files, color files, exemplary to use.
While developing the Android application.
So it is the responsibility of the resource manager to maintain it.
Then comes the telephony manager.
It manages all mobile device functions like the SIM management and the network management, etc. Then
comes to window manager, window manager managers, all the open windows.
So each activity is basically built with a window.
So we will learn more in more detail about Windows in a later session that we discuss about the Windows
management system.
And then providers and then providers allow data to be shared between different applications within
the system.
View System.
View System is responsible for building the essential view components of an application.
So it's basically responsible for inflating your layouts.
And these layouts has multiple types of views.
So the view system is basically responsible for rendering these different views onto the screen.
The system runtime library layer is divided into two parts the C C++ library and the Android runtime
library.
Let's discuss about them separately.
So let's first look at the C C++ library.
The C C++ library can be used by different Android system components and provide developers service
through that application framework.
So all the services which we use through the application are dependent on this C C++ library.
Below are some examples of C C++ libraries.
So the first one is OpenGL ES OpenGL for embedded systems.
So this is basically a 3D drawing function library specifically designed for embedded devices.
Then we have the Lipsey ellipses, basically the standard C system function library inherited from BSD.
BSD stands for Berkeley Software Distribution.
And this is specially customized for embedded Linux based devices.
And then we have the media framework.
So this contains the library which supports recording and playback of various commonly used audio and
video formats like M.P. three, MP four, etc...
And then we have the squirrel light.
This is a lightweight, relational database engine.
This, again, a lightweight solution created for mobile devices.
And then we have is still and still stands for Simple Graphics Library.
So this is the underlying 2D graphics rendering engine for Android.
And then we have SSL, this very common security protocol.
So the sector socket layer is a security protocol that provides security and data integrity for network
communication.
And then finally, we have the free type.
This is basically to manage the different varieties of fonts.
So this is basically a portable font engine.
It provides a unified interface to access a variety of font file formats.
So these are some of the major C C++ libraries found in Android system runtime layout.
The runtime library is divided into core library and ATA early stands for Android runtime.
The code library provides small.
Most of the Java language gold library functions so that developers can use the Java language to write
Android applications.
So the purpose of code library is to simply provide Java language code library functions.
Now, regarding the Dalvik virtual machine or API, dalvik virtual machine can be compared with Java
virtual machine, but the Dalvik virtual machine is specifically customized for mobile devices.
It allows multiple instances of virtual machine to run in the limited memory simultaneously, and each
Dalvik application is executed as an independent Linux process.
So since we have separate process, it prevents all programs from closing when the virtual machine crashes.
So that is the main advantage since we have different process.
Even if the virtual machine is virtual machine crashes, then it will prevent from all the apps or the
programs from being closed.
So the reason why Dalvik virtual machine was migrated to RB is that they are to provide some advantages
compared to dalvik formation.
So under Dalvik, the bytecode needs to be converted into machine code by a just in time compiler every
time the application is run.
So Dalvik basically used a just in time compiler.
So whenever the application runs, it has to convert the code information code.
This will slow down the programming efficiency of the application because whenever the application starts
up, it has to be first converted information code and then run the app.
This will actually slow down the execution speed of the app.
With the introduction of RB after Android file.
The code of all the application will be pre compiled in the mission code when it is first installed
in the device.
This makes the application a true local application.
In this way, Arity makes the app execute faster compared to Dalvik.
Now let's look at the hardware abstraction layer.
The hardware abstraction layer is the interface between the operating system kernel and the hardware.
Its purpose is to abstract the hardware to protect the intellectual property rights of the hardware
manufacturers.
It hides the hardware interface, details of a specific platform and provides a virtual hardware platform
for the operating system so that it has hardware independence.
It can be transplanted on various platforms.
From the perspective of software and hardware testing, both software and hardware testing can be completed
based on the hardware abstraction layer, making it possible to perform software and hardware testing
in parallel.
So in layman's term, a bypass of hardware abstraction layer is to control the hardware.
But let's look at the Linux kernel layer, which is the bottom most layer in Android.
Android ecosystem services are dependent on the Linux kernel and some Android specific drivers.
For example, audio display, keypad, Bluetooth, USB, etc. have been added on this basis.
The Android System Security Memory Management Process Management Network Protocol Stack and driver model
depends on this Linux kernel, which makes Android in a way more secured and stable.
So that's about the Android architecture.
Understanding this bilayer, Android architecture will help you when we analyze the system source code
in the later tutorials.